Hi everybody, today's דף Daf is נד. Nun Dalet. We start towards
the bottom of נג עמוד ב. Nun Gimmel Amud Bet. תנו רבנן
מעשה באחד. Tanu Rabbanan ma'aseh b'echad.
It's about 15 lines down in the wide lines, line starts with
the word באחד. b'echad. Okay,
מעשה באחד, ma'aseh b'echad, so we've been discussing putting a covering over
the udder of cows or goats on שבת, Shabbos, whether that's considered
something that they can be wearing on שבת. Shabbat. So that leads
to a little digression here about a story about nursing. Very interesting
story, let's take a look. תנו רבנן מעשה באחד, Tanu Rabbanan ma'aseh
b'echad, a story with a certain person, שמתה אשתו, she-meisah ishto, his
wife died, והניחה בן לינק, v'henichah ben l'yanek, and he left and
she left over a child that's still needed to nurse, ולא היה
לו שכר הניקה ליתן, v'lo hayah lo sechar yenikah litten, and he
was poor, he didn't have the money to hire a wet nurse.
And so what's he supposed to do? That was before the advent
of baby formula. ולא
שכר הניקה ליתן, v'lo sechar yenikah litten, ונעשה לו נס, v'na'aseh lo
neis, and a miracle happened, ונפתחו לו דדין כשני דדי אשה, v'niftachu
lo dadin k'shnei dadei ishah, and he developed breasts like women's breasts,
והניק את בנו, v'heinik et b'no, and he nursed his son. So
אמר רב יוסף, amar Rav Yosef, said רב יוסף, Rav Yosef, בוא
וראה כמה גדול אדם זה, bo re'eh kamah gadol adam zeh, look
how great this person is, שנעשה לו נס כזה, she-na'aseh lo neis
kazeh, such an amazing miracle happened to transform the normal way of
nature.
So אמר ליה אביי, amar leh Abaye, אביי Abaye said to him,
אדרבה, adarabbah, the opposite is true, כמה גרוע אדם זה שנשתנו לו
סדרי בראשית, kamah garua adam zeh she-nishtanu lo sidrei bereishit, how, you
know, lowly is this person that nature
had to change for his sake. So it's quite an interesting question,
you know, because in the תורה, Torah, of course, you have these,
these miracles which are about transforming nature,
but obviously חז"ל Chazal were living in a time when you did
not have these blatant miracles and you did not have obvious sort
of violations of natural law. And here you actually have, so one
is saying, oh my gosh, that's amazing, such a miracle, such an
obvious miracle, and the response being actually, no, nowadays, you know, the
idea is God works within nature, not that God works by violating
natural laws. That's one way of understanding it as a certain like
a theological debate about the idea of seeing God's hand nowadays,
and, you know, should we, are we looking for supernatural miracles. It
could also be very much that it was about this person individually,
you know, that this thing happened to his body and that like
his, you know, as a man, he transformed into having, you know,
being somewhat like a woman. So could be that that's the issue
as well, this like crossing of a gender lines and what happened
to him as a person, you know, that could be the concern,
but it could seem be as I said, a more just broader
theological issue about looking for God in nature or in something in
the supernatural. Let's see how, one minute, let's see how the גמרא
Gemara concludes. It says, אמר רב יהודה, amar Rav Yehudah, בוא וראה
כמה קשין מזונותיו של אדם. bo re'eh kamah kashin mezonotav shel adam.
Come and see how difficult it is finding,
earning, getting, making a living, making enough money so that you can
feed yourself. שנשתנו לו סדרי בראשית, she-nishtanu lo sidrei bereishit, that, you
know, it was so difficult rather than God making it that he
could find a פרנסה, parnasah, find a job, this happened to happen
that this a supernatural thing had to happen that his body had
to develop breasts so he could nurse,
basically, right, or he exactly, I think that's part of the concern
here, not just that it's supernatural, but that it's crossing this male
female boundary. But so look, you know, so why didn't God just
help him find a job? So it must be that it's very
difficult even through God working through nature to help people who need
to find a job. And this is interesting, other גמרות Gemaras as
well talk about this about, you know, about the fact that it
acknowledged how challenging it is, can be for people to find a
job and for to get a פרנסה. parnasah. So אמר רב נחמן,
amar Rav Nachman, תדע, Teida, you should know that this is true,
true, דמיסטרחי שיניתו ולא איברו מזוני. de-misrachei shineitav v'lo ivru mezonot. We
see, maybe he means in this case, maybe he means in general,
that miracles happen and nevertheless we don't, you know, it might be
things that seem miraculous occur, but we don't see things that are
just helping people get an easier job, get an easier פרנסה. parnasah.
So it must be getting a פרנסה parnasah is really hard and
it's easier for other types of miracles to occur. So quite fascinating
in terms of that sense of number one, you know, גמרא Gemara
sort of speaking about, especially the בבלי Bavli where again I don't,
one had a sense that the things that both, you know, the,
the host government there, the, the life in בבל Bavel was, was
more beneficial to the Jews, not just politically but also economically and
still this sort of discussion about how difficult it is, you know,
to find a job and also this issue here about whether God
we're looking for God to operate within nature or above nature. Now
I did want to make a comment about this issue about this
person who's able to nurse from I looked this up the other
day from Scientific American, strange but true, males can lactate.
Men have all the necessary equipment to produce milk and on occasion
it happens. Okay, and then it says like this, it says,
"You're going to say that." It says like this: "There have been
countless literary descriptions of men miraculously breastfeeding, from the תלמוד Talmud to
Tolstoy, where in Anna Karenina there's a short anecdote of a baby
suckling an Englishman for sustenance while aboard a ship." So it actually
says it can sometimes happen due to if the stimulation of the
nipples but also needs to be a release of a certain hormone,
which it actually says will sometimes be released if somebody is actually
starving, in starvation. So it's actually quite interesting that the גמרא Gemara
says that this person had no money, right, and he couldn't get
a job and he actually was breastfeeding his child, so at least
according to Scientific American, there could be some link to that that
if a person is undernourished that might cause the release of that
hormone. Yes, Michael.
Maybe say that even in the context of okay it's hard to
have a job than to have a miracle, so I don't quite
understand why that would be, you know, theologically. Right. The miracle could
have also happened that, you know, he bought a fish one day
and then he found a pearl in it.
Yeah, I don't know.
That would also be
amazing and he wouldn't have to have... I don't know what the
answer to that. Okay, so let's continue. תנו רבנן Tanu Rabbanan מעשה
באדם אחד שנשא אשה גידמת, Ma'aseh b'adam echad shenasah isha gidemet,
a certain man married a woman who was lame.
Wait, גידמת gidemet is missing a hand? Yeah, גידר gider is lame,
right? גידם gidem is missing a hand.
That's what I meant. Isn't that that you don't call that lame?
Lame is only in the leg? Leg? Oh, I'm sorry. Okay, fine.
Thank you. Okay, a woman missing an arm. Thank you. ולא הכיר
בה עד יום מותה, velo hikkir bah ad yom motah,
and he did not recognize this until she died. אמר רב, Amar
Rav, so said Rav or Rebbi, בוא ראה כמה צנועה אשה זו:
bo re'ei kama tzenuah isha zu: see how, you know, how modest
this woman was, שלא הכיר בה בעלה, shello hikkir bah ba'alah, her
husband that they lived a whole life, it's very interesting, right, it's
right after the whole Rachel-Leah story, you could live together and the
fact she could have totally have hid this from him their entire
life together. אמר ליה רבי חייא, Amar lei Rebbi Chiya, so Rebbi
Chiya said to Rebbi, זו דרכה בכך: zu drakah bekach:
this one it's her way, meaning in general maybe we expect women
to be modest and number two, she's got something she needs to
hide. So that's not the חידוש chiddush that she was able to
hide it or that that she tried to hide it. אלא כמה
צנוע אדם זה: ella kama tzenua adam zeh: but how modest is
the husband, שלא הכיר באשתו, shello hikkir b'ishto,
he didn't know about it. So you would have expected that he
would have wanted to have seen, you know, seen his wife and
fully and
nevertheless he was whatever he went, he followed her lead and or
he himself was very modest and therefore they were able to live
together without ever having seen one another fully or him seeing her
fully and seeing this. So it's interesting on the one hand the
גמרא, Gemara, you know, the גמרא Gemara associates this with modesty but
there's other גמרות Gemaras gets into other issues, you know, about how
much the גמרא Gemara sort of thinking that husband and wife should
not be, you know, naked together, looking at each other naked together,
I mean there's other גמרות Gemaras that say that actually it's a
biblical requirement of עונה onah that they sleep together naked, not just
that they have sex. So it's interesting, you know, trying to sort
of bring all the גמרות Gemaras together about attitudes it had towards
modesty particularly within the marital context and whether this is, you know,
a good thing or not a good thing, you know, to be
sort of completely not looking at your partner. But anyway this is
at least this גמרא. Gemara. Yes.
It's definitely not just modesty but
now imagine how well she was able to manage in the kitchen
at raising children with one hand.
That's really rough. Oh, interesting. Right. What an amazing...
Oh, interesting, צנועה tzenuah not that he didn't look at her, right,
but
the fact that she, you know, had this lack... Uh-huh. That's interesting.
...and everything that a woman would do on...
Huh, that's a fascinating read. Thank you. Okay, I don't see how
it fits in the גמרא's Gemara attempt to frame it as modesty,
צנועה. tzenuah.
Well, that's their attempt.
Right, but you're saying maybe part of the point of that whole
story is exactly this, not just, right, not just שלא הכיר בה
shello hikkir bah in the physical sense but שלא הכיר בה shello
hikkir bah in terms of everything she was doing in the house,
she was able to do it, right, without
him to see her.
Right. Very nice. Okay.
Maybe he wasn't home a whole lot of time at home.
Yeah. Right. Let's be cynical. Yes. Alright, so now the גמרא Gemara
back to the halachic discussions of the משנה Mishnah about what animals
can be having wearing on שבת Shabbat or what would be considered
a burden and carrying. זכרים יוצאין בלבובים: zacharim yotzin belevuvin:
so rams can go out with לבובים. levuvin. What does this mean?
Wearing some type of a thing called לבובים levuvin
or wearing this is referred to as לבובים. levuvin. So מאי לבובים,
mai levuvin, what is this? אמר רב הונא תותרי: Amar Rav Huna
totari: so it's תותרי. totari. That doesn't help. What's תותרי? totari? So
so רב Rav says here let me find the רש"י, Rashi, רש"י
Rashi says two lines down שמחברים אותם בקשר שנים שנים שלא יברחו:
shemechabrim otam bekesher shenayim shenayim shello yivrachu:
they basically you you tie them together as pairs. Okay, so you
can't tie together two rams as pairs. So מאי משמע דהאי לבובים
לשנא דקרובי הוא: mai mashma dehai levuvin lishna dekaruvei hu: where do
you see that that means bringing together? דכתיב לבבתני אחותי כלה: dichtiv
libavtini achoti kallah:
so you have loved me my sister the bride, so לבבתני libavtini
to love or לבוב levuv is means to like bring together. So
you pair them off and you tie them together. tie them together.
So somehow that is considered to be something that is, you know,
maybe done for business purposes or other things, but not directly to
protect the ram, and therefore the ropes that are around them that
are tying them to one another is a burden. עולא אמר, Ulla
amar, עור— or I’m sorry,
so thank you, thank you, I’m sorry, I got confused, right. You’re
right, רב Rav points out things that they can do. Thank you.
So they can go out. So right, it’s Rabbi Yossi who really
rejects all this, but the תנא קמא Tanna Kama says it’s okay.
So that is interesting. Right, so according to the תנא קמא Tanna
Kama presumably this is something that is considered something that is normal
for them or something that helps to protect them, maybe stop them
from running away.
עולא אמר, Ulla amar, עור or שקושרים shekoshim להם lahem כנגד kneged
ליבם. libam. You actually bind a type of a leather opposite their
heart כדי kedei שלא shelo יפלו yiplu עליהם aleihem זאבים, ze'evim, so
that wolves don’t attack them. So this is really to protect them
then, and presumably the wolf would attack at their, you know, at
their heart. So the גמרא Gemara says: זאבים ze'evim אדכרים adikarim נפלי,
nafli, אנקבות anekevot לא lo נפלי? nafli? So why is it only
the rams? What about the female sheep? The wolves will attack them
as well. So the גמרא Gemara says: No, משום mishum דמסגי demasgei
בריש bereish עדרא. idra. So no, because the rams walk at the
head of the flock and therefore the wolves see the rams. So
the גמרא Gemara says: ובריש uvereish עדרא idra נפלי, nafli, בסוף besof
עדרא idra לא lo נפלי? nafli? So I don’t get it, they
only attack the head of the flock? They don’t attack the rear
of the flock? אלא ella משום mishum דשמיני. deshmeini. So because they’re
fat and they look, they’re the juiciest animal, so therefore they get
attacked. So the גמרא Gemara says: ובנקבות uvenekevot ליכא leika דשמיני? deshmeini?
What, you're telling me there's no, you know, fat, good-looking female sheep?
ותו v'tu מי mi ידעי yadei הני hanei להני? lahanei? What, can
they really tell, like which are the fat ones and not the
fat ones when they come to attack? אלא ella משום mishum דזקפי
dezakfi חוטמייהו chotmaihu because their noses are up, their heads are always
raised ומהלכי umahalechu כי ki דאוי davi and they're walking and they're
sort of looking around. So apparently the rams, the rams as opposed
to the sheep, so the rams’ heads are more high up and
רש״י Rashi says that that somewhat sort of instigates the wolves, they
sort of see that as threatening and therefore that they attack.
So why did Rabbi Yossi disagree?
I don’t know. Anyway, so this is some type of a way
of protecting them from attack which was seen necessary, more necessary by
the ram. רב נחמן בר יצחק אמר, Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak amar,
עור or שקושרים shekoshim להם lahem תחת tachat זכרותם zachrutam כדי kedei
שלא shelo יעלו ya'alu על al הנקבות. hanekevot. And this’ll be similar
to how we explained the issue by the female, well that too,
but the female lambs, I mean sheep. So it’s something that you
tie by their genitals in order to prevent them from copulating. ממאי,
mimai, how do you see this? מדקתני midekatani סיפא seifa because it
fits in, it’s parallel to
the end, ורחלים verachelil יוצאות yotzot שחוזות. shuchuzot. They go out שחוזות.
shuchuzot. מאי mai שחוזות? shuchuzot? What does שחוזות shuchuzot mean?
שאוחזים she'ochzim האליה ha'alyah שלהם shelahem למעלה lemala כדי kedei שיעלו sheya'alu
עליהם aleihem
זכרים. zecharim. So specifically it’s relating to copulating, except here instead of
preventing it, it’s in order to enable copulating, you hold up the
fat tail so that the male sheep can go up on them.
So the גמרא Gemara says: רישא reisha כדי kedei שלא shelo יעלו
ya'alu על al הנקבות, hanekevot, סיפא seifa כדי kedei שיעלו sheya'alu עליהם
aleihem זכרים. zecharim. So therefore it sort of parallels, that’s not a
question actually, that’s an explanation. So the same way, so it’s all
relating to copulating. First we talk about doing something to the rams
to prevent them and then we do something about the sheep to
enable it. Well, different times you want them either to copulate or
not copulate, different times of the year, or if you’re Yaakov from
last week’s פרשה, parshah, depending on whether they’re the ones with the
spots or not. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says: מאי משמע
mai mashma דהאי dehai שחוזות shuchuzot לישנא lishna דגלוי degiluy הוא? hu?
Where do you see שחוזות shuchuzot means to expose them? It seemed
before we’re doing שאוחזים, she'ochzim, to hold, but how do you know
שחוזות shuchuzot means to expose them for the sheep? דכתיב dechtiv והנה
vehinei אשה ishah לקראתו likrato behold a woman was there to greet
him, שית shit זונה zonah ונצורת unetzurat לב, lev, like dressed as
a prostitute and of a wily heart. So שחוזות shuchuzot is somehow
some combination of שית shit זונה zonah and I don’t know, שחוזות
shuchuzot it seems to be some version of those words. Anyway, so
it means exposed particularly sexually. Okay, so that’s, now we’ll just end
this because now we are going to have the opposite case of
trying to protect the sheep from copulating, from being, you know, from
having the rams go up on them. ורחלים verachelil יוצאות yotzot כבולות.
kevulot. So the משנה Mishnah said what are the ways in which
the female sheep can go out, so mentioned the following, it said
שחוזות, shuchuzot, כבולות, kevulot, וקבונות. ukvunot. So we mentioned שחוזות shuchuzot which
was with the fat tail up and now we’re going to say
what is כבולות kevulot and that’ll be the opposite. מאי mai כבולות?
kevulot? What does כבולות kevulot mean? שמחבלין shemechablin אליה alyah שלהם shelahem
that you basically tie down, you bind their fat tail on them
למטה lemata below כדי kedei שלא shelo יעלו ya'alu עליהם aleihem הזכרים
hazcharim in order to prevent them from the rams from copulating. So
sometimes you want the sheep to copulate and sometimes you don’t. מאי
mai משמע mashma דהאי dehai כבול kavul לישנא lishna דלא dela עביד
avid פירי peiri הוא? hu?
Where do you see this language of כבול kavul means to in
order to not, you know, in order to not be fertile? In
order to not produce fruit, דכתיב dechtiv because it says, by Hiram,
he's complaining to Shlomo and he says מה הערים האלה אשר נתתה
לי אחי? ma hearim haele asher natata li achi? What are these
cities that you gave me, my brother? says Hiram, who helped Shlomo
build the Beit HaMikdash, ויקרא ארץ כבול עד היום הזה. vayikra eretz
kavul ad hayom hazeh. So he was upset about the land and
it was called the land of כבול, kavul, so presumably כבול kavul
somehow means non-fertile land. So מאי ארץ כבול? mai eretz kavul? But
now what does that mean? So first we're going to have sort
of something not as directly about this. אמר רב הונא שהיו בה
בני אדם שמחובלים בכסף ובזהב. amar rav huna shehayu bah bnei adam
shemechubalin bakesef uvazahav. There were people that were sort of like bound
up, you know, with gold and silver. So somehow כבול kavul here
does not mean not fertile, it means bound. But bound could also
work; the fat tail was bound against them to prevent them from
copulating. So the Gemara says אמר ליה רבא אי הכי היינו דכתיב
ולא ישרו בעיניו? amar lei rava i hachi hainu dechtiv velo yashru
be'einav?
That Hiram was not happy with them. מפני שמחובלים בכסף ובזהב לא
ישרו בעיניו? mipnei shemechubalin bakesef uvazahav lo yashru be'einav? Because the people
there were surrounded with gold and silver, why was Hiram upset? So
אמר ליה אין, amar lei in, yes, he was upset, כיון דעתירי
ומפנקי, keivan de'atirei umifankei, since the people the city were so rich
and delicate, לא עבדי עבידתא, lo avdei avidta, they would not be
willing to work in the, you know, be drafted for the king's
army or the king's work. So I don't know, at least tax
them then! But okay. Anyway, but there כבול kavul means bound, so
like the fat tail is bound. רב נחמן בר יצחק אמר ארץ
חומטין היתה.
rav
nachman bar
yitzchak amar eretz chumtin hayta.
It was a very sort of dry and cracked, parched earth. ואמאי
קרי ליה כבול? ve'amai kari lei kavul? Why is it called כבול?
kavul? דמשתקעא בה כרעא עד כבלא. demishtake'a bah kera'a ad kavla. So
or maybe not dry, but whatever, it was cracked, it was muddy
and your ankles would go submerge in the land, your feet would
submerge until your ankles. ואמרי אינשי, ve'amri inshi, and people would say,
ארעא מחבלא, ara mechavla, this is a land of כבול, kavul, דלא
עבדא פירי, delo avda peiri, that you did not make fruit. Which
explains that's the exact language the Gemara uses initially. We never said
that the word כבול kavul meant not fertile, we just said it
meant that the fat tail was bound, but presumably there was this
idiom of ארץ כבול דלא עבדא פירי, eretz kavul delo avda peiri,
a land of כבול kavul that is not fertile, does not bear
fruit, and therefore we are trying to connect it to that idiom,
and here we're connecting it to this story of Shlomo. So I
want to just stay here. So it becomes quite fascinating then that
what you are allowed to do in this Mishna, I mean Rabbi
Yosei disagrees, but according to the Mishna is you're allowed to, the
ram can go up with something tied on him to prevent him
from, you know, from copulating; the sheep can go with something either
to prevent copulation or to enable copulation. That's not a problem on
Shabbat. Now that seems to violate everything we've been talking about because
until now basically the argument has been that something that is there
for the sake of helping protect the sheep, stopping it from run
away, that's acceptable. Something that is there that would be, let's say,
for your usage of it, you know, for you to sort of
derive benefit from it, like I don't know, you know, a saddle
or whatever, it's not there for protection, that's considered a משוי. masoi.
So this type of a thing is not protecting the sheep, you
know, in terms of their physical well-being, it's not stopping them from
run away, it's just serving like your economic interests that you don't
want them either to copulate or you do want them to copulate
at this time. And nevertheless it's not considered a burden. And it's
very funny, like people don't really talk about, you know, conceptually what
are the categories here. To me it seems you have to say
one of two things based on this Gemara. Now Rabbi Yosei does
argue on this, so at least it's not universally accepted, but according
to this opinion either it's really not an issue of, you know,
protecting versus non-protecting. It's really an issue of like norms. What is
sort of seen as the norm for it to be wearing it
like at all times or most times, that's not a burden, and
what's considered as something that doesn't normally wear, you know, it's not
always on it, that's a burden. So during certain times of the
years, presumably this would always be on the rams or it would
always be on the sheep and therefore it's more of an issue
of norm versus not norm and not a clear category of function.
The other way to think about it is is that this is
something that protects your interests as the owner, your financial interest, but
it's not you using the sheep. Meaning the other types of things
maybe had to do more with the way you would use it,
like you would put a saddle on it and you would use
it. Here you're not using it, here it's sort of it's protecting
your it's serving your financial interest but it's less about your use.
But I don't know if that really fits all of the cases
because we even saw certain types of ornamentation were considered a burden.
That's not about you using it, it's just not needed for it
to be on. So it does seem that at least according to
this position, it's less about protecting the sheep and more just about
a question about what's the norm is not a burden, what goes
beyond the norm is a burden. Okay, so that's these positions about
the various things that are around the sort of copulating of the
sheep. And now the Gemara goes to the last one, כבונות. kvunot.
The sheep can also go out כבונות. kvunot. מאי כבונות? mai kvunot?
What does this mean? שמכבנין אותם למילה. shemechabnin otam lemila. Somehow you
cover up again, I don't know the word מכבנין. mechabnin. Rashi says
actually word כבינתי, kvinati, another famous Gemara that he says which means
that right, that it's some type of a thing, some type of
a of a that you hook over them or you wrap them
up in order to. What? Is that Merino? But the Cashmere is
what
I was thinking of.
No, it comes, doesn't come from a sheep. It comes, is it
Merino?
But isn't there something else
what they said like if something is a wool? What am I
thinking of?
Are you thinking about alpaca?
I don't know what I'm thinking of. Okay, Merino. Okay, fine. Anyway,
okay, so anyway, so the גמרא Gemara says שאת, se-eis, שאת se-eis
which is one of the colors of צרעת tzara'at of
leprosy, כצמר לבן ketzemer lavan like white wool. מאי צמר לבן? mai
tzemer lavan? What does it mean white wool? So אמר רב ביבי
בר אביי, amar Rav Bibi bar Abaye, כצמר נקי בן יומו ketzemer
naki ben yomo
like one day old wool שמכבנין אותו למילה she-mechabnin oso le-mila that
you had always been covered from the time the sheep was born
in order to protect it to create this very fine wool. So
again, that's protecting your financial interests. I mean it's protecting the sheep
and not the sheep's health, it's protecting the sheep's wool for your
financial interest and somehow that still is considered to be totally acceptable
and not a problem. And remember that's in contrast to the covering
of the udder to catch the milk. So what's the difference? Although
there maybe it was carrying the milk or it was loose and
it would have fallen off. But again it is interesting and it's
very hard to get a handle on exactly what the different line
is about what is a burden and what is not unless you
say it's something to do with norms. העזים יוצאות צרורות, ha-izim yotzot
tzerurot, so here exactly goes this issue, goats can go out bound
with their udders bound. So here we have
the משנה Mishna ended by saying that the goats can go out
with their udders bound. רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi says none of this
is acceptable, the rams, the sheep, the goats, except for the one
thing that to me at least might have seemed to be more
problematic, except for the sheep כבנות kivunot with their wool covered. Somehow
that seems to be the most that's protecting your financial interests but
no, somehow that's acceptable, maybe because it's also somehow protecting something that
is still attached to the body of the sheep. But he says
all of that is no good which at least makes a little
more sense because as I said it's hard to understand why this
isn't a burden. ורבי יהודה ve-Rabbi Yehuda makes the distinction between if
the udders are bound ליבש le-yavesh to dry up the milk which
is okay or לחלב le-chalav to catch the milk which is no
good. So איתמר itmar was taught, רב אמר הלכה כרבי יהודה. Rav
amar halacha ke-Rabbi Yehuda. We rule like Rabbi Yehuda that distinguishes between
whether it's drying up the milk or catching it. What's the difference?
It's two possibilities: drying up the milk might be that it's tight
so it won't fall off. If it's there to catch the milk
it might fall off and therefore it's a rabbinic issue. The other
possibility is that tying up, stopping the milk is seen as a
way of for the sake of the animal, if it's no longer
nursing then it's in pain as it continues to lactate, whereas catching
the milk is there for protecting, you know, carrying the milk and
you're protecting your investment. It's not there for the animal. So he
rules like Rabbi Yehuda. ושמואל אמר הלכה כרבי יוסי, ve-Shmuel amar halacha
ke-Rabbi Yossi, no we rule like Rabbi Yossi that says it's all
אסור assur except for the case of the wool. ואיכא דמתני להא
שמעתא באפי נפשה, ve-ika de-masni ha shem'ta be-apei nafsha, some teach this
separately. רב אמר ליבש מותר ולא לחלב, Rav amar le-yavesh muttar ve-lo
le-chalav,
in order to dry up the milk is okay on the goats
but not in order to catch the milk. So that's like Rabbi
Yehuda. ושמואל אמר אחד זה ואחד זה אסור, ve-Shmuel amar echad ze
ve-echad ze assur, it's all forbidden, this whole thing is אסור, assur,
the only one thing maybe is this wool case. ואיכא דמתני להא
ve-ika de-masni ha and some teach this debate on the following teaching:
עזים יוצאות צרורות ליבש אבל לא לחלב, izim yotzot tzerurot le-yavesh aval
lo le-chalav, this is a ברייתא. Baraisa. The sheep can go out
with their udders bound for drying up the milk but not for
the sake of catching the milk. משום רבי יהודה בן בתירה אמרו
כך הלכה, mishum Rabbi Yehuda ben Beseira amru kach halacha, in principle
that's the law. אבל מי מפיס? aval mi mafis? Who is going
to throw lots? Meaning who's going to be able to distinguish איזה
ליבש ואיזה לחלב? eize le-yavesh ve-eize le-chalav?
I'm going out with my sheep's udders covered, you're not, it all
looks the same to the outsider so people aren't going to make
a difference so they're going to all say it's always okay. So
since people will say it's always okay because who can tell which
is for the sake of drying and which is for the sake
of catching the milk, we have to forbid it all. So it's
all forbidden. In principle you're right, there is a distinction but in
practice we have to forbid it all. ומתוך שאין מכירין אחד זה
ואחד זה אסור. u-mitoch she-ein mekirin echad ze ve-echad ze assur.
And because people can't distinguish we have to say it's all forbidden.
אמר שמואל ואמרי לה אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל הלכה כרבי יהודה
בן בתירה. amar Shmuel ve-amri la amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel halacha
ke-Rabbi Yehuda ben Beseira. We rule like Rabbi Yehuda ben Beseira that
it's all forbidden. כי אתא רבין אמר רבי יהודה הלכה כתנא קמא.
ki asa Ravin amar Rabbi Yehuda halacha ke-tanna kamma. And then there's
another position which is we go like the תנא קמא tanna kamma
which says it's all permissible whether it's to stop them from copulating
and to catch the milk and it's all okay. So again no
discussion in the גמרא Gemara what this debate is about, as I've
been saying, to say it's forbidden makes sense, these are things that
are not to protect the animal, they're somehow to protect your financial
interests and therefore it's considered a burden. The real hardest thing is
to distinguish between the position that says it's okay. What makes this
okay and other things not okay? And again it seems like you
have to say that it's more about a question of what was
the norm versus not the norm as opposed to the function that
these things were doing. Okay, so now yes.
What about walking a dog on a leash?
Oh, so actually we
have
a... So the leash we're about to get to, you are, you
know, you're, what's it, clairvoyant? Because that's the next משנה. Mishnah. So
let's take a look at the next משנה. Mishnah.
Okay,
okay. So it says like
this: ובמה אינה יוצאה ובמה אינה יוצאה, Uvameh einah yotzah uvameh einah
yotzah, what
can the animal go out with? לא יצא הגמל במטולטלת. Lo yetzei
hagamal bemetulteles. The camel cannot go out with a מטולטלת. metulteles. What's
a מטולטלת? metulteles? רש"י Rashi has a couple of explanations. Either it's
a type of again a saddle, a saddle blanket, or רש"י Rashi
actually thinks that it's something that you put sort of under its,
under its tail in order to, in order to protect it from
like, let me just see the רש"י Rashi here.
Yeah, yeah, רש"י Rashi says that you would actually have a strap
in order for the, that you would go, run under the tail
in order to protect like the, you know, the, what do you
call it? The load from falling off, and in order to protect
it from the rubbing of the strap, you would put this type
of a pillow underneath the tail. So that's what רש"י Rashi says
it is. Okay. And therefore it makes sense that you can't wear
it on שבת, Shabbos, because its whole purpose is for the time
of when you're having it carry a burden. לא עקוד ולא רגול.
Lo akud velo regul. It can also not be עקוד, akud, like
עקידת יצחק, Akidat Yitzchak, and it cannot be רגול. regul. It cannot
have its leg bound up. These are things that stop it from
walking, but again maybe it's not just, it's considered to be maybe
painful and therefore a burden or something that's not strictly necessary in
order to prevent it from walking around. וכן שאר כל הבהמות, Vechein
shear kol habeheimot, and similarly all other animals, לא יקשור, lo yikshor,
you cannot have them with their legs bound. We'll clarify this in
the גמרא. Gemara. לא יקשור גמלים זה בזה וימשוך, Lo yikshor gemalim
zeh bezeh veyimshoch, do not tie camels one to another, you know
those pictures they have about like them all in this nice little
row. Don't do that and walk them on שבת. Shabbat. אבל, Avel,
again assuming you're walking them in a place where there's an עירוב.
eruv. אבל, Avel, or maybe not, we'll see in a minute. אבל,
Avel, because you're not actually picking it up and carrying it, they're
just really walking themselves, so strike that. אבל מכניס חבלים לתוך ידו
וימשוך, Avel machnis havalim letoch yado veyimshoch, you can have multiple straps
in your hand and
drag them along with you even as long as they're not lined
up in a row, as long as each one is sort of
a separate strap that goes to your hand. We will see in
the גמרא. Gemara. ובלבד שלא יכרוך, Uvilvad shelo yichroch, but don't wind
the straps around your hand. Hard to understand what all the issues
are here, what is the problem. So let's take a look at
the גמרא. Gemara. תנא: Tana: לא יצא הגמל במטולטלת הקשורה לו בזנבו.
Lo yetzei hagamal bemetulteles hakeshurah lo biznavo. Should not go out with
this מטולטלת metulteles underneath its tail, again for רש"י Rashi it's some
type of a pillow. אבל יוצא הוא במטולטלת הקשורה בזנבו ובחוטרתו. Avel
yotzei hu bemetulteles hakeshurah biznavo uvehotarto. But it can go out with,
with one of these pillows which is down to both its, to
both underneath its tail and on its hump. So why is it
better if it's on both? So רש"י Rashi actually says that, that
the problem here is less that it's a burden and more of
an issue that we're afraid that it'll fall off. So therefore, if
it's bound both at the tail and around the hump, keeps this
thing on the camel, whatever it is. Again, רש"י Rashi goes back
and forth between saying it's a type of a saddle blanket or
it's a type of a pillow underneath the tail. But if it's
bound in two places underneath the tail and around the hump, then
it won't slide off and it's okay. And why is it never
a burden? So that I don't know. Again, maybe because it's for
the comfort of the camel. Again, I by this stage I have
sort of given up trying to figure out what the dividing line
is other than saying again, what's the norm versus not the norm.
And then, okay, yes?
Maybe it's because any movement of the saddle cloth will cause pain,
and so maybe the idea of pain?
Right, that's what I'm saying. Right, right, but that, so yes, that's
what, you mean if it's not fully bound? Right, right. רש"י Rashi
also says the common concern here is, and the גמרא Gemara isn't
always spelling it out, A) it might be that it's defined as
a burden, B) it might fall off and then we're afraid you'll
carry it. So I get it, I understand, I understand. I get
it, I get it. אמר רבה בר רב הונא: Amar Rabbah bar
Rav Huna: יוצא גמל במטולטלת הקשורה לו בשלייתא. Yotzei gamal bemetulteles hakeshurah
lo beshalyata. Similarly if it's bound to its placenta, afterbirth. Again, I
don't understand, apparently camels, animals would sometimes have this and they, they
would not fully expel it immediately right after birth, but somehow that
will be, it will not, that because it's painful if it tries
to get, get out of this, you know, out of the strap
because it's connected to the afterbirth, therefore it won't try to get
out of the strap and it won't fall off. So רש"י Rashi
reads this whole thing as a question of whether it will fall
off or not, and if it's bound in a way that it
won't fall off, it's not a problem. Okay. לא עקוד ולא רגול.
Lo akud velo regul. Not bound or, you know, or רגול regul
or its leg bound up. So what do these mean? אמר רב
יהודה: Amar Rav Yehuda: עקוד, Akud, bound, like עקידת יד ורגל, Akidat
yad varegel, means that you bind the hand and the leg. the
foot together. So the left hand to the left foot and the
right hand to the right foot. כייצחק בן אברהם, Ke'Yitzchak ben Avraham,
like יצחק, Yitzchak, like that was עקידת יצחק. Akeidas Yitzchak. Now, how
do we know that was עקידת יצחק? Akeidas Yitzchak? I have no
idea, but somehow they knew that was עקידת יצחק. Akeidas Yitzchak. So
that's what עקוד akud means.
Normally when you see the picture when people, artists' rendition of עקידת
יצחק, Akeidas Yitzchak, it's not that way, is it? It's more like
the hands together and the feet together, right? Okay, anyway.
Okay,
רגול, ragul, and what does רגול ragul mean? שלא יכוף ידו על
גבי צוארו ויקשור. shelo yachof yado al gabi tzvaro v'yikshor. Basically you
make it three-legged. You take one of its legs and you bend
it up and you tie the ankle towards the top of the
thigh. So therefore it can't move with that leg and therefore it
can't run away. So presumably if it can't do this, you do
this so it doesn't run away. So why is this considered to
be a burden? Before we had that the normal types of things
that prevented it from running away, the collars and whatnot, were okay.
So presumably you have to say that this is either, if it's
painful, maybe that by itself defines it as a burden. That would
be interesting, but the גמרא Gemara doesn't say that. Or maybe it's
just seen as excessive. This was and it goes back to the
idea before that something that maybe is an excessive protection is a
burden, but that was debated. But somehow this is seen as not
necessary and a burden as opposed to certain other things. Yes.
These large animals need all four legs. Why would this be permitted
not on שבת? Shabbos?
Well, maybe you don't want it to run away. You've got a
big camel,
so you tie it down.
Yeah, apparently this was a common practice. But maybe you're right, maybe
because this was not seen, the גמרא Gemara does not, the משנה
Mishnah does not condemn this practice. But maybe somehow because it was
seen as excessive or painful or something of that nature is why
it's considered a burden. But again, I really, this is all speculated.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara asks on this, מיתיבי, Meseivi, I'll ask
you on this. עקוד שתי ידיו ושתי רגליו, akud shtei yadav u'shtei
raglav, we have a ברייתא Baraisa that says עקוד akud means the
hands together and the feet together. And עקידת יד ורגל, akeidas yad
v'regel, I'm sorry, I skipped a line. ושתי רגליו. u'shtei raglav. רגול,
ragul, and רגול ragul means שלא יכוף ידו על גבי צוארו ויקשור,
shelo yachof yado al gabi tzvaro v'yikshor, like you said, bending up
the leg. So you see it doesn't mean foot and
arm together. הוא דאמר כי האי תנא. hu d'amar k'hai tanna. No,
he goes like the following תנא. tanna. דתניא ותנא ברייתא, d'tanya v'tanna
Baraisa, עקוד עקידת יד ורגל או שתי ידיו
ורגליו. akud akeidas yad v'regel o shtei yadav u'raglav. That says עקוד
akud means either hand and foot or the two hands and the
two feet separate. רגול שלא יעקוף ידו על גבי צוארו ויקשור. ragul
shelo ya'akof yado al gabi tzvaro v'yikshor. So
the גמרא Gemara says, and רגול ragul is like we said. So
the גמרא Gemara says, וקמייתא לא דמי, v'kamaisa lo dami, it's not
similar. בשלמא רישא וסיפא ניחא, bishlama reisha v'seifa nicha,
the beginning and the end are good, it's exactly what you said,
that עקוד akud means hand and foot and רגול ragul means the
leg bent up. במציעתא קשיא, b'metziata kashya, the middle doesn't work, because
that says hands together and feet together and you didn't include that.
אלא הוא דאמר כי האי תנא, ela hu d'amar k'hai tanna, he
says like the following תנא, tanna, that says עקוד עקידת יד ורגל
כיצחק בן אברהם רגול שלא יעקוף ידו על גבי צוארו ויקשור, akud
akeidas yad v'regel Ke'Yitzchak ben Avraham, ragul shelo ya'akof yado al gabi
tzvaro v'yikshor, like he said originally, which says עקוד akud is hand
and foot, רגול ragul is leg bent up, and does not have
the case of hands together feet together. And actually the שולחן ערוך
Shulchan Aruch rules this way. I know saying rules this way is
a little funny for us, we don't tend to have these animals
around, but actually the relevance being that it says that hands together
and feet together would be considered an acceptable and normal way of
protecting the animal, stopping the animal from running away, and would not
be a burden. So again, it's quite interesting what exactly is the
difference how you're binding them. Presumably one form of binding is again
seen as maybe again, I'm speculating, but maybe painful for the animal
is a factor, makes it more of a burden, or excessive. But
again, excessive was debated before. Anyway, so therefore but we do have
somehow some of these things are, others scenarios are not considered to
be a burden. Maybe again, the easiest thing is to say it's
an issue of what was the norm and what was not the
norm. ולא יקשור גמלים, v'lo yikshor gemalim, now we get to slightly
different things other than the burden issue. Do not have the camels
go in a line. מאי טעמא, mai ta'ama, what's the reason? אמר
רב אשי משום דמיחזי כמאן דאזיל לחינגא. amar Rav Ashi mishum d'meichzi
k'man d'azil l'chinga. It looks like you're going to the market. If
you're walking with your camels in a line, it looks like you're
not just taking them out for a walk, it looks like you're
going on a journey to bring your wares and to sell them,
which is obviously a very non-שבת Shabbos activity. Now, you could explain
this, I've said this before, as a מראית עין. marris ayin. You
don't do something that looks bad, people will suspect you, whatever. But
I think it's much more directly a שבת Shabbos issue about it's
not what we would call שבתדיק. Shabbos'dik. You're creating an, you're doing
an experience that is a very much a weekday experience and not
only for you privately, it's done in public so it affects the
public sort of atmosphere, culture of שבת Shabbos that people are walking
their camels, it feels like, makes it feel like the weekday. So
therefore that is not something we do on שבת. Shabbos. Nothing to
do with carrying. אבל מכניס, aval machnis, you can put the ropes
in your hand, the individual ropes in your hand, but don't wrap
them. So now we have to see what the problem of wrapping
them is. אמר רב אשי לא שנו אלא בכלאים. amar Rav Ashi
lo shanu ela b'kilayim. It's only a problem about wrapping it about
כלאים, kilayim, שעטנז. shaatnez. What's שעטנז? shaatnez? כלאים דמאי, kilayim d'mai, what
type of שעטנז? shaatnez? אילימא כלאים דאדם, eileima kilayim d'adam, maybe the
problem is, you're not allowed to work your donkey, your mule and
donkey together, and you can't use any two animals together. So as
my son would say, well, people are animals too. So what about,
so what about if you and your, and they actually you know
sometimes they did this, they were poor whatever, you would bind you'd
bond like part of the plow to you and part of the
plow to your horse and together you would plow with the plow.
So is that כלאים, kilayim, is that two separate animals together, you
a human and an animal? So the גמרא Gemara says no,
so the גמרא Gemara says no it's not. דתנן אדם מותר עם
כולם לחרוש ולמשוך. de-tenan adam mutar im kulam lachrosh u-limshoch. A man
can plow and drag drag with the other animals, it's just two
different non-human animals. So it can't be that that's the concern that
you're going to be somehow doing a work together with the camel.
אלא כלאים דחבלים, ela kilayim de-chavalim, you're concerned about the ropes. If
you've maybe some ropes are linen and some ropes are wool and
you wrap them together, maybe you twist them together something like that
and then they're warming your hand and it's a שעטנז shatnez problem.
And that's why you can't wrap them. והתניא ve-hatanya but we taught
in the ברייתא braita התוקף תקיפה אחת אינו חיבור. ha-tokef tekifa achat
eino chibur. If you take a wool and linen piece of garment
and you just put one stitch to put them together that's not
enough to make שעטנז. shatnez. So how does just wrapping them
around your hand make שעטנז? shatnez? So גמרא Gemara says לעולם כלאים
דחבלים. le-olam kilayim de-chavalim. Like we were saying the ropes are a
problem that wool and linen ropes will make שעטנז. shatnez. והכי קאמר
ve-hachi ka-amar ובלבד שלא יכרוך u-vilvad shelo yichroch don't wrap them ויקשור
ve-yikshor and tie them together. Okay so therefore be careful not to
wrap and tie the ropes together that might be a שעטנז shatnez
issue. Presumably it was relatively common to have them tied both on
your hands, right,
and is that enough to make שעטנז, shatnez, tying something like that?
Well presumably it says wrapping and tying like maybe you twisted them
and then you knotted them, you twisted them together and you knotted
them all together. Yeah well then basically not necessarily. I mean there's
a lot of it might very well be to really make biblical
שעטנז shatnez you probably have to do a lot more like twist
the individual strands together or something but it could be certainly there's
a category of rabbinic שעטנז shatnez where it's less. Okay so apparently
the גמרא Gemara feels it's enough without unpacking whether it's biblical or
rabbinic as long as you twisted them and knotted them you're certainly
already in some type of שעטנז shatnez category. אמר שמואל amar Shmuel
so now but other than that you're fine. So now by the
way and this gets to Riska's important question. Here you are you're
walking your camel on שבת. Shabbat. How are you walking your camel
on שבת Shabbat and we had it before a strap on a
collar right and the גמרא Gemara spoke about the various straps and
תוספות Tosafot talks about having a strap on your horse and walking
with your horse or whatever it is how can you do it
why is it not carrying?
And you know I was looking for some discussion about this because
this is even brought down להלכה le-halacha about you can walk with
them as long as you don't sort of in this case twist
them around. Couldn't find a good discussion but I'll look some more
but it seems that once you're saying that it is considered to
be clothing or not a burden for the animal then it's not
a carrying problem. Like for example let's say we didn't have an
עירוב eruv and I don't know I had a big hat with
a big brim and I was afraid it was going to fly
away and you were holding on to that brim you know to
keep my hat down. You wouldn't be carrying my hat just because
you're holding my hat because it's on my body and I'm wearing
it. So if you say that the collar and the strap are
not considered are considered sort of a normal thing to be on
the animal an acceptable thing then you as the owner holding the
strap you're not carrying. And
the animal isn't carrying, it's not, it's a type of clothing for
the animal it seems.
I know a leash isn't clothing, it's a collar.
Well the גמרא Gemara again what defines as clothing the גמרא Gemara
seems to see that things that are on the animal for the
sake of protecting it and stopping it from running away doesn't have
to directly define as clothing just define it as like a non-burden.
And that seems I mean so that seems to be we discussed
before this idea of having straps and leashes and those cases where
that was normal for the animal that was actually seen as okay.
But you have to ask the question of burden for whom because
the collar really
is really protecting the owner.
Yeah I know so that's somehow we said yes I understand it
protects the owner's interests but somehow because it's the norm to be
on the animal or because you know the animal somehow by being
under the control of the owner doesn't get into other trouble you
know somehow that's seen as being as non-burden. Let's read let's read
a little more. Let's read a little more. So the גמרא Gemara
says like this, אמר שמואל amar Shmuel ובלבד שלא יצא חבל מתחת
ידו טפח. u-vilvad shelo yetze chevel mi-tachat yado tefach. So you can
hold on to this rope and lead your camel, that's fine, but
don't have the rope coming a טפח tefach outside of your hand
from the end not the camel end the other end. Why? So
רש"י Rashi says then it won't be obvious that you're just holding
on to the camel then it'll look like you're holding on to
a piece of rope I don't know for somebody's not looking at
the whole thing anyway and it'll look like you're carrying the piece
of rope. Okay so והא תנא דבי שמואל ve-ha tana de-bei Shmuel
but one minute from the ישיבה Yeshiva of שמואל Shmuel they teach
טפחיים tefachayim it's only a problem with two טפחים tefachim outside of
your hand. אמר אביי התם דאמר שמואל טפח ותנא דבי שמואל טפחיים
שמואל להלכה למעשה אתא לאשמועינן. amar Abaye hatam de-amar Shmuel tefach ve-tana
de-bei Shmuel tefachayim Shmuel le-halacha le-maase ata l-ashmueinan. So yes it's really
two טפחים. tefachim. Why is שמואל Shmuel telling us one טפח? tefach?
In order to sort of you know in practice it's better to
you know tell people one טפח tefach so therefore they'll be a
little bit more careful but in principle it really is two טפחים.
tefachim. only a problem when it is two טפחים, tefachim, two טפח.
tefach. דתניא ובלבד שיגביה מן הקרקע טפח. Detanya uvilvad sheyagbi'ah min hakarka
tefach. You have to keep the strap a טפח tefach off of
the ground or the lead. So כי תניא ההיא בחבלא דביני ביני,
Ki tanya hahi bechavla deveini veini, that's not the part coming out
of your hand away from the camel, that's the part between your
hand and the camel. If it's low to the ground also it
doesn't look like you are, you know, holding on to a camel,
like walking your camel, it looks like you're dragging a rope, a
strap, and therefore it is a problem. So as long as you
keep, you know, the leash off of the ground and it doesn't
come out of your hand a טפח, tefach, right, according to this
it would be מותר muttar to even walk your dog without an
עירוב. eruv. Now I looked into it a little yesterday, I'll try
to look into it more, but again it's fascinating because you would
have started think why, it's to be carrying, you're carrying the leash,
but somehow it seems like that's not an issue of carrying once
it's not considered a burden for the animal.
Yes, because it's only a problem if it's כלאים, kilayim, which means
a
non-Jew can do that too.
Correct. Correct. But then isn't that a little bit strange that
they're throwing something in left field, has nothing to do with...
Yeah, I know. I know.
Yeah, that's a different story. Picking up after your dog, picking up
after your dog is a whole issue about מוקצה, muktzah, גרף של
רעי, graf shel rei, protecting other people from stepping into the poop.
And obviously if there's no עירוב eruv that would be a carrying
issue as well. Right, so this we're just talking about the walking,
not the other parts. Yes.
Can't you take a... you use a rope with a camel to
lead the camel. Right. You use a leash on a
dog to stop it from running away. Exactly. But it would seem
that that's better from the perspective of this גמרא. Gemara. That the
initial גמרא Gemara spoke about the more it's there to
stop the animal from running away, the more it's acceptable to be
an עירוב. eruv. That's right. Exactly. Yeah, and somehow the משנה Mishnah
allows even by the camel even though it's about leading. Okay, so
let's take a look now, now we continue. אין חמור יוצא במרדעת
בזמן שאינה קשורה לו. Ein chamor yotzei bemardaat bizman she'einah keshurah lo.
The donkey cannot go out with a saddle blanket if it's not
tied up to it from before שבת. Shabbos. The גמרא Gemara said
earlier ולא בזוג אף על פי שהוא פקוק, Velo bezug af al
pi shehu pakuk, and not with a bell even though it is
stopped. There's a stopper in it so it's not making noise, which
obviously would be a problem, the making like ringing of the bell
on שבת. Shabbos. ולא בסולם שבצוארו, Velo besulam shebetzavaro, if they would
sometimes put like a ladder or something that looked like a ladder
along the length of the neck of the donkey to stop it
from or the mule, excuse me, to stop it from—no, I was
right the first time—the donkey
to stop it from like turning its head. We'll see why in
the גמרא. Gemara. That would not be acceptable. ולא ברצועה שברגליו, Velo
biretzuah sheberaglav, not the strap that they would sometimes put on its
legs, we'll see what that's about. ואין התרנגולים יוצאין בחוטין, Ve'ein hatarnagolim
yotzin bechutin, chickens cannot go out with strings, ולא ברצועה שברגליהם, Velo
biretzuah sheberagleihem, or straps on their legs, we'll see what this is
all about. ואין הזכרים יוצאין בעגלה שתחת האליה. Ve'ein hazcharim yotzin be'agalah
shetachas ha'alyah. The rams cannot go out, sometimes they would have little
wagons because the rams would have these huge fat tails and they
would drag against the ground and they would get scraped or whatever
so they tie little wagons on the back of the ram to
to hold the fat tail. Now again, you'd assume that if that's
to stop part of its body from getting damaged, you would assume
that's totally acceptable. So I really don't know what the logic here
is again unless you go back to what was the norm or
not the norm which is a little bit, you know, doesn't give
you any clear, you know, conceptual category. That would not be acceptable
ואין הרחלים יוצאות חנונות. Ve'ein harechelim yotzos chanunot. And the female sheep
cannot go out חנונות, chanunot, we'll see what that means, the גמרא
Gemara will say it's something up their nostrils in order to deal
with some ailment. ואין העגל יוצא בגימון, Ve'ein ha'egel yotzei begimon, the
עגל egel which is the calf cannot go out with a גימון,
gimon, we'll see what that is in the גמרא. Gemara. ולא פרה
בעור הקופר, Velo parah be'or hakupar, and not a cow with the
leather of a קופר kupar which is a hedgehog or something like
that anyway to protect, stop other animals from nursing from it if
it's if it's nursing. ולא ברצועה שבין קרניה, Velo biretzuah shebein karneha,
or a strap between its horns. פרתו של רבי אלעזר בן עזריה
היתה יוצאה ברצועה שבין קרניה. Parato shel Rabbi Elazar ben Azaryah hayata
yotzah biretzuah shebein karneha. You know what? רבי אלעזר בן עזריה's Rabbi
Elazar ben Azaryah cow would wear a strap between its horns to—no,
or a string, שלא ברצון חכמים, Shelo birtzon chachamim, and the rabbis
were not happy with it, it was against their... to their displeasure.
Very fascinating, let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. מאי טעמא?
Mai ta'ama? So first about the saddle blanket, what's the reason? כדיאמרין,
Kidi'amrin, like we said before, which is interesting because the גמרא Gemara
discussed the saddle blanket, it basically said if it's not bound from
before שבת, Shabbat, it's not bound at all, it's because it'll fall
off. If it's not bound from before שבת, Shabbat, then a different
reason is either that it looks more of a burden or it
looks more like you're going out for business, various types of concerns
about binding it on שבת, Shabbat, the saddle blanket. ולא בזוג אף
על פי שהוא פקוק, Velo bezug af al pi shehu pakuk, and
not with the bell even if it's stopped. משום, Mishum, same issue,
דמחזי כמאן דאזיל לחינגא. demichzei keman de'azal lechinga. You walk out with
your donkey with a bell around or Bessie with a bell around,
it looks like you're heading off to the market even if the
bell isn't ringing and as we said that is a problem on
שבת, Shabbos, it's a very weekday type of an activity to be
doing. Now תוספות Tosafot says why did you need that reason? Why
don't we just say the bell is not... is basically there as
a type of ornamentation? That's what תוספות Tosafot thinks and or certainly
if it's stopped. Stopped up, it's not protecting it in any way,
and you know תוספות Tosafot thinks that ornamentation is always a problem.
So some ראשונים Rishonim say again this issue of norms, ornaments that
are normally there are okay, not normally there are not okay, but
you would think a bell is probably normally there. It's pretty in
sync with the norm. So תוספות Tosafot basically says we have to
say that the bell is like woven into the halter, like little
bells on the halter like you have the reindeer, whatever you have
the little bells and therefore it's not carrying per se because the
halter is okay. It's just an issue of looking like you're going
to the market. That's the way תוספות Tosafot explains it. Okay, ולא
בסולם שבצוארו Velo basulam shebetzavaro
and not with the ladder
on its neck, alongside its neck. So
where were we? אמר רב הונא Amar Rav Huna בלועי beluai it
goes by the sort of jowls and the cheeks. למאי עבדי ליה
Lemai avdi leh what do they use this for? להיכא דאית ליה
מכה Leheicha d'it leh maka if it's got some type of a
wound דלא הדר חייך בה delo hadar hayech beh you don't want
it turning its neck and like scraping at its wound, so you
do this to keep the neck straight. So why can't you do
it? It's doing some type of a health thing, you know, some
type of... but again, somehow it's not, I really don't
know. Somehow it's not seen there as some type of a clothing
for the animal.
Is that like
some psychosomatic term?
Yeah, well, no. ולא ברצועה שברגליו Velo birtzuah sheberaglav not with a
strap by its legs. דעבדי ליה לגזרא D'avdi leh l'gizra you do
it to protect. Rashi says לגזרא l'gizra means
that where it's like knock-kneed or something, you would put a strap
there to allow it to walk well, okay, and or to prevent
it from getting worse. And all these things are seen as burdens
and extraneous. I mean, they're for health, but somehow they're not seen
as a type of a clothing of the animal as a natural
thing to be on the animal. Look, for people as well you
could do things for health, but under certain circumstances, if they're not
there serving a clothing function, it's not acceptable. The problem is by
animals, we haven't exactly defined it as clothing, we've tried to say
like it's not helping them, it's a burden and again, we're a
little bit lost at what is the dividing line here. ואין התרנגולים
יוצאים בחוטין V'ein hatarnagolim yotzim bechutin so the chickens can't go out
with strings. דעבדי ליה סימנא D'avdi leh simana that you would put
a strings on your chickens כי היכי דלא ליחלפו ki heichi d'lo
lichlefu so you know who are my chickens and who are your
chickens or identifying strings. Okay, so again, something we would think, okay,
that's maybe a normal type of thing for it to be wearing.
Again, I really don't know. Yes, Charlie.
Collars on cats with identification tags.
Ah, if the whole purpose is to identify them. Aha, that's interesting.
Maybe that would be different.
Although now now cats are getting surgical microchips.
Now now
cats go out against our will.
Right.
I really if I knew what the rule what the principle was
here, I might be able to answer this. I mean, it's interesting
that even though this was relevant to the ראשונים, Rishonim, you don't
see a lot of development of this in the ראשונים Rishonim and
in the
תשובות Tshuvot literature. I mean they did have a lot more of
these they were farmers. Well, some of them had farmers. Well, that's
true, maybe they didn't have these things on their
animals. Okay, okay. ולא ברצועה Velo birtzuah or not the strap דעבדי
ליה כי היכי דלא ליברו מאני d'avdi leh ki heichi d'lo livru
mani you maybe put a strap on the legs of the chickens
so that they would not go around and kick things and break
them, so it would sort of prevent their legs from moving
too much of an angle. They can't go out with. Well, that's
obviously to protect other people's property, that's not for them. ואין הזכרים
יוצאים בעגלה V'ein hazcharim yotzim ba'agala you cannot make this wagon for
the fat tail כי היכי דלא לחמטן אייתא ki heichi d'lo lachmatan
ayata so that the fat tail should not scratch. Again, seems like
a pretty legitimate purpose, but maybe because it's a wagon, it's somehow
seen as again something external and not clothing and not whatever and
seen as a burden. ואין הרחלים יוצאות חנונות V'ein harachelim yotzot chanunot
the sheep cannot go out חנונות. chanunot. יתיב רב אחא בר עולא
קמיה דרב חסדא Yativ Rav Acha bar Ulla kamei deRav Chisda יתיב
וקאמר yativ veka'amar בשעה שגוזזין אותה beshaa shegozezin otah we're trying to
figure out what this חנונות chanunot is. When you shear them, טומנים
לה עזק בשמן tomnim lah azak beshemen you take some like soft
cloth, cotton Rashi maybe and oil, ומניחין לה על פדחתה uminichin lah
al padachtah and you put this nice oil cloth on its forehead
כדי שלא תתצנן kedei shelo titztanen that it does not get a
chill after you've just sheared it, it's naked. So that's what this
חנונות chanunot means is
some type of a cloth you put on the forehead in order
to prevent it from getting a chill. Again, it's doing a health
thing, but it's seen as external to the animal. It's still seen
as a burden. So the גמרא Gemara says אמר ליה רב חסדא
אם כן עשית מר עוקבא Amar leh Rav Chisda im ken asita
Mar Ukva you've turned your sheep into מר עוקבא. Mar Ukva. Meaning
that that type of a thing that if somebody's not feeling well
you put a wet towel on their head, that's what you do
for people and not only normal people you do it for very
חשוב chashuv people like מר עוקבא, Mar Ukva, he gets that treatment.
The sheep doesn't get that treatment. So that can't be what we're
talking about. אלא יתיב רב פפא בר שמואל קמיה דרב חסדא Ella
yativ Rav Pappa bar Shmuel kamei deRav Chisda יתיב וקאמר yativ veka'amar
here's what it is. בשעה שכרעת לילד Beshaa shekarat leiled when it
is actually in the process of giving birth, it's bending to give
birth. טומנין לה שני עזקים של שמן ומניחין לה אחד על פדחה
ואחד על רחם. tomnin lah shnei azakim shel shemen u'manichin lah echad
al padekha v'echad al recham.
Same idea. You basically take these two cloths and you put them
in oil and you put one on its forehead and one on
its womb כדי שתתחמם k'dei shetitchamem in order that it could actually
as opposed to before in order that it should warm up it
should just so similar to what we said before except here during
childbirth not after it's sheared. So אמר ליה רב נחמן amar lei
Rav Nachman so רב נחמן Rav Nachman said אם כן עשית יאלתא
im kein asita Yalta
then you've turned them into יאלתא Yalta which was רב נחמן's Rav
Nachman wife. Says that's what we do for our women when they're
giving childbirth. We don't do that same fancy treatment for the sheep.
It's so funny like did they do it or didn't they do
it for the sheep? They're debating whether it's oh that's too fancy
for the sheep. אלא Ella good thing they didn't see nowadays how
people treat their poodles whatever. אלא אמר רב הונא Ella amar Rav
Huna עץ אחד יש בכרכי הים eitz echad yesh b'charkhei hayam here's
what it is.
There's one type of a wood a tree in the islands וחנון
שמו v'chanun shemo it's called חנון chanun like חנונות chanunot was with
the phrase of what you were doing. ומביאים קיסם u'mevi'im kisam you
take a splinter from it ומניחין לה בחוטמה u'manichin lah b'chotmah you
put it in its nostrils כדי שתתעטש k'dei shetit'atesh so it should
sneeze ויפלו דרני ראשה v'yiplu darnei rasha and the various lice or
whatever that are in its head should come out. So the גמרא
Gemara says אי הכי i hachi if that's what it is זכרים
נמי zecharim nami why is it only for the female? Before we
said it was about shearing them or it was about childbirth so
then we understood the female but according to this why is it
only the female sheep? ומהא דזאת u'me'ha d'zot so the גמרא Gemara
says no כיוון דמנגחי זכרים בהדדי kivan d'menagchi zecharim bahadadi since the
rams butt heads ממילא נפלי mimeila nafli so then that gets the
bugs out of their hair. But the female sheep they need this.
Okay but they can't go out with this right? They need it
but they don't go out with it on שבת Shabbat but that's
what it's doing. שמעון נזירא אמר Shimon Nazira amar שמעון Shimon the
נזיר Nazir said interesting קיסם דריתמא kisam d'ritma again it's a piece
of a wood but it's
of this other thing called רתמא ritma
I forget how they translate רתמא ritma there. They say what it
is? Some other type of wood. Okay so some other what? Broom
tree. Now we know. Broom tree. בשלמא דרב הונא bishlama d'Rav Huna
so according to רב הונא Rav Huna I get it היינו דקתני
חנונות hainu d'katani chanunot it's called חנונות chanunot because the name of
the tree is a חנון. chanun. אלא לרבנן ella l'Rabbanan מאי חנונות
mai chanunot for the Rabbis what does it mean חנונות? chanunot? Why
is that what's used for these cold compresses or hot compresses or
whatever they are? דעבדינן להו מילתא דמרחמינן עליהו d'avidnan lehu milta d'merachminan
aleihu because from the word of חנון chanun you do something to
have compassion over them you try to alleviate their pain when childbirth
or after shearing. But again although all of these things or many
of these things are done for health purposes even for people we
learned before that if you have a bandage that is there to
keep a salve on but not functioning to protect the wound directly
then that's considered a not clothing and a problem. So here too
even if it's for the sake of the animal somehow if it's
seen as external and not it's seen as a burden and it
is a problem. Okay ואין העגל יוצא בגימון v'ein ha'eigel yotzei b'gimon
the calf does not go out with a גימון. gimon. מאי עגל
בגימון mai eigel b'gimon what does that mean? אמר רב הונא amar
Rav Huna בר נירא. bar nira. It's a type of a little
yoke that you would put even on a young calf to train
it because you've got to sort of actually I've heard that this
is true you've got to sort of put these the yokes on
the animals earlier they learn too much independence and they won't take
a yoke when they're older. So אמר רב אלעזר amar Rav Elazar
מאי mai משמע mashma since that's really weekday related. So מאי משמע
דהאי גימון לישנא דמיכף mai mashma d'hai gimon lishna d'michaf so where
do you see this word גימון gimon means to bend down? דכתיב
הלכוף כאגמון ראשו d'chtiv halachof k'agmon rosho will he bend his head
like an אגמון agmon which normally is translated as what? Like a
willow or something. Anyway so here you see it means to bend
down. What is it? Interestingly the אבן עזרא Ibn Ezra says a
fishhook. A fishhook is an אגמון agmon that's interesting. Okay. Is it
bulrush? Bulrush. That's what I always thought. That's what it says the
Artscroll יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. Alright ולא פרה בעור הקופר v'lo parah
b'or hakupar so again all these things are done but this clearly
is not done for the sake of the animal somehow for
the sake of the owner.
Anyway these things even if they're done for the sake of the
animals as we said are somehow seen as
extraneous they're not they're not sort of
a type of a clothing they're still seen as a burden. So
what's this why would you put this leather on the udder? דעבדי
לה כי היכי דלא למציוה יאלי d'avdi lah ki heichi d'lo lamtziuha
yali so יאלי yali which רש"י Rashi says are some certain type
of a rodent should not nurse from the cow. Leeches right whatever
it is. Apparently they would do it to protect other animals from
nursing from it and somehow this was seen as less of a
more extraneous than when you were trying to catch the milk or
when you were trying to dry up the udder that was seen
as okay different opinions about that here it's seen as something that
is again somehow less acceptable. ולא ברצועה שבין קרניה v'lo b'retzu'ah shebein
karneiha not the strap between its horns. אילימא רב Ilima Rav בין
לנוי בין לשמר bein l'noy bein l'shamer רב Rav said in an
earlier גמרא Gemara whether the strap is there for ornamentation or whether
to protect it אסור assur it's forbidden because even to protect it
ornamentation is certainly extraneous but even to protect it it's considered unnecessary
protection. It's a cow it's easy to protect. אילימא שמואל Ilima Shmuel
שמואל אמר Shmuel amar לנוי אסור l'noy assur only for ornamentation it's
a problem that's a burden לשמר מותר l'shamer mutar if it's done
to protect the cow that's okay. Elazar's cow disagreed with that again
I guess. Or right. פרתו של רבי אלעזר בן עזריה *Parato shel
Rabbi Elazar ben Azarya*. So the גמרא *Gemara* says חדא פרה הוי
ליה *Chada para havi lei*? His cow? Did he only have one
cow? It didn't say one of his. Said his cow. ואמר רב
ואמרי לה אמר רב יהודה אמר רב *Ve'amar Rav ve'amrei lah amar
Rav Yehuda amar Rav* תריסר אלפי עגלי *Treisar alfei eglei* 12,000, one
imagines this is a bit of an exaggeration, 12,000 calves הוי מעשר
רבי אלעזר בן עזריה מעדריה כל שתא *havi masar Rabbi Elazar ben
Azarya me'edreih kol shata*. That would be his tithes every year from
his flock. So he did not just have one cow. כל שתא
ושתא *Kol shata ve'shata*. So the גמרא *Gemara* says תנא *Tana* so
fine we taught in the ברייתא *Beraita* לא שלו היתה *lo shelo
hayeta* it wasn't literally his. אלא ששכנתו היתה *Ella she'shchenato hayeta* it
was his neighbor's. ומתוך שלא מיחה בה *Umitor shelo mikha bah* because
he did not stop her from doing it, נקראת על שמו *nikret
al shemo* it's called his, he had to take responsibility. And this
now leads us into an interesting discussion about the responsibility to tell
others you know to intervene if something wrong is happening even if
you're not the one doing it and we'll just read one last
statement about this. רב ורבי חנינא ורבי יוחנן ורב חביבא *Rav, Rabbi
Hanina, Rabbi Yohanan, ve'Rav Haviva* these four Rabbis and then the גמרא
*Gemara* interrupts and says מתנו בכוליה דסדר מועד כל כי האי גוונא
*matnu be'khulei deseder Moed kol ki hai gavna* whenever we teach in
מועד *Moed* this list of these four Rabbis there are חלופי רבי
יוחנן ומאי רבי יונתן *khalufey Rabbi Yohanan umai Rabbi Yonatan* there are
those that exchange רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yohanan* for רבי יונתן *Rabbi Yonatan*.
So that was parenthetical. Anyway, back to the point. These four Rabbis
said כל מי שאפשר למחות לאנשי ביתו *kol mi she'efshar limkhot leanshey
beito* anybody that could like stop you know prevent the people in
his household, probably means his wife and children, from acting incorrectly ולא
מיחה *velo mikha* and you did not you know protest נתפס על
אנשי ביתו *nitpas al anshey beito* then you are grabbed, you are
held accountable for their sin. Okay, באנשי עירו *be'anshey iro* if you
could stop the people of your city from doing something and you
don't נתפס על אנשי עירו *nitpas al anshey iro* then you're held
accountable for the whole city. ובכל העולם *Vekhol ha'olam* if you could
stop the world from doing something wrong and you don't כולו *kullo*
then נתפס על העולם כולו *nitpas al ha'olam kullo* you're responsible. If
you do not intervene then you are held accountable for the sins
of others when you could have done something about it. Okay and
now the גמרא *Gemara* ends with at least for now by saying
אמר פפא והני דבי ריש גלותא *Amar Pappa vehani devei reish galuta*
the people from the house of the ריש גלותא *Reish Galuta* they
have power and authority and they could you know control intervene by
whatever people are doing ניתפסו אכולי עלמא *nitpasu al kulei alma* they
have the responsibility when anybody does something wrong because they're in a
position to do something about it. So we will continue in this
vein tomorrow.